# **Karen Jacks**

# **Retail Management Professional**

20, Hartford Road, Northwich Cheshire CW9 8JE | 07549 558942 | Karenb1955@me.com

## **Personal Profile**

Experienced Retail Management Professional with a comprehensive background in Commercial Business Development and Project Management.

Developing key internal relationships and strategic partnerships across a broad base of disciplines through effective communication, an assured decision maker with a purposeful approach to achieving goals and profitability.

Working through people and teams in an inclusive approach, with the ability to direct, lead and manage operationally and tactically in order to achieve Operational Excellence and Customer Satisfaction.

I am an energetic and enthusiastic leader, proactive and resourceful in my approach Confident and purposeful whilst insuring a motivational and inspirational team culture leading to high performance and delivery of results. Equally committed to personal growth.

# **Areas of Expertise**

Strategic Leadership P&L Management Business Development

Project Planning & Delivery Strategic Planning Operational Excellence

People & Personal Development Change Management Marketing & PR

## **Professional Experience**

Dec 2014 – Aug 2017

#### **Retail Project Manager – Property Division**

IKEA UK London

- Lead the Retail Implementation of New Store Builds, Commercial re –
  developments of new or existing properties in the UK Property Portfolio –
  including contribution to the UK 40-year Market Share Expansion Plan –
  Specifically IKEA Greenwich preparation
- In conjunction with Global, Real Estate and Construction partners deliver the IKEA Concept with Time, Cost and Quality methodologies
- Delivery of the IKEA Band into the Local Market, building political and local support, including building Strategic Community relationships
- Devised and implemented processes, procedures, systems and internal controls to strengthen operations, increase productivity and enhance customer satisfaction and develop the Property Division
- Coach, Lead and develop the Retail Implementation team to deliver the Project Implementation Plan

• IKEA UK Member of the Green Building Council – Property Division ambassador in Sustainable Building Development

Dec 2009 - Dec 2014

#### **Store Manager**

IKEA UK

Coventry

- Develop, lead and deliver a long term plan for sustainable Business Growth and profitability with Sales in excess of 75 million £
- Position the IKEA Brand in the local Market in all media and communication channels
- Lead 360 co-workers to established a culture of commitment to an exceptional Customer experience
- Demonstrate and develop high performing leaders and empowered teams contributing to the Business Plan
- Contribute to IKEA UK and Global Projects acting as an Ambassador for the Country UK
- Ensuring implementation and adherence to expectations and legal requirements for H&S, environmental and quality management systems including Food.

Mar 2007 - Dec 2009

### **UK Project Leader**

IKEA UK

London

- Leading a Project Management team in the implementation of a UK HR Shared Service Centre, a Global Implementation Project
- Implementation and development of the Global Project Process including IT and introduction of SAP
- Recruit and prepare shared service centre physical space including development of new process and process improvement methodologies
- Develop and implement process of Change Management and training of 10, 000 UK co-workers
- Contribute to the Global Implementation plan including supporting "new "Country Implementations

Jun 2006 - Mar 2007

## **Deputy Store Manager**

**IKEA UK** 

Birmingham

- Support the Store Manager in the development and delivery of the IKEA Business plan to secure Business Growth and Profit turnover 150 million £
- Lead the Store Commercial Team
- Secure the IKEA Vision through the Store and Web experience
- Develop the Commercial Leadership
- Contribute to IKEA UK on national Projects Ambassador for the UK for Retail Development
- Ensure the delivery of all Health and Safety legal requirements in area of responsibility and total store
- Deputise for the Store Manager and lead the Store Team

Sept 2004- Mar 2006

### **Area Manager (and Deputy Retail Director)**

Mothercare London

- Lead the Business development of the London Area, specifically the Flagship stores
- Attend weekly Board meetings bringing field information, risks and opportunities to the Board
- Support and develop the Country Sales and Profit Growth Plan
- Recruit and develop leadership of the Units

1989-2004

#### **Arcadia and the Burton Group**

Area Manager West End, London

Retail Project Manager London Store Manager Manchester

1977 - 1989

#### **Debenhams**

Deputy Store Manager
Finance and Operations Manager
Bolton
Top Shop Manager
Logistics Manager
Menswear Manager
Chester
Concession Manager
Chester
Chester

#### Education

1972 – 1977 Ellesmere Port Grammar School for Girls